<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sites>
    <site>
        <name>Battlefield Park</name>
        <lat>32.074696</lat>
        <lon>-81.09729</lon>
        <img>battlefieldpark</img>
        <desc>The site of the bloodiest battle of the American Revolution</desc>
        <longDesc>
            Battlefield Park is the site of the bloodiest battle of the American Revolution. You are standing where
the Colonial and French Allies attacked the Spring Hill Redoubt on October 9, 1779. Fourteen redoubts,
or small forts, connected by an abatis wall surrounded British-held Savannah during the American
Revolution. The Allied casualties numbered approximately 800, while the British only 50. The Allies
retreated in chaos, losing the battle but eventually winning the war.

Along Martin Luther King Jr. Blvd rises a reconstructed Spring Hill Redoubt, about ¾ its original size.
A few hundred feet down Louisville Road, a memorial marks the remains of the original Spring Hill
Redoubt discovered in 2005 by Coastal Heritage Society archaeologists. Look for plaques around
the park that give a detailed history of the battle and a column of stones commemorating the Allies’
casualties.

After the Revolutionary War, houses and small business sprung up including a distillery and meat-
packing industries. In the 1830s, the area changed drastically again with the founding of the Central of
Georgia Railroad.</longDesc>
        
        <!-- Image followed by description -->
        <evImg>battlefield_ev1</evImg>
        <evDesc>Brass barrel band from a Charleville pistol</evDesc>
    </site>
    <site>
        <name>Madison Square</name>
        <lat>32.073575</lat>
        <lon>-81.093877</lon>
        <img>madisonsquare</img>
        <desc>Location of a military ditch dug by British forces in 1779</desc>
		<longDesc>
		    In 2008, archaeologists discovered a military ditch dug by British forces in 1779. Angling northwest-
southeast, this ditch was identified as the West-Central redoubt, which was the location of Allies’ feint
before real attack at Spring Hill.

After the British left Savannah in the summer of 1782, the Americans filled in the ditches, burying
many artifacts as well. Brick from the barracks located just north was found in the ditch. Many of these
artifacts tell us about the lives of the soldiers.
		</longDesc>
        <evImg>maddison_ev1</evImg>
        <evDesc>Archaeologists excavating in Madison Square.</evDesc>
        
        <evImg>maddison_ev2</evImg>
        <evDesc>Military button found in Madison Square excavation, note the faint “V”.</evDesc>
    
    	<evImg>maddison_ev3</evImg>
    	<evDesc>Guncock from a British Brown Bess musket recovered from the Madison Square excavation.</evDesc>    	    
    </site>
    <site>
        <name>Lafayette Square</name>
        <lat>32.073084</lat>
        <lon>-81.091912</lon>
		<img>lafayettesquare</img>
		<desc>Historical maps suggest this is the location of the East-Central redoubt</desc>
		<longDesc>
		    Historic map analysis suggested that the East-Central redoubt was located in Lafayette Square, so
archaeologists conducted a ground penetrating radar survey and dug several test pits (holes) in the
northwest quadrant of the square. Archaeologists found many artifacts from the 1730s to 1770s

including a .28 caliber lead ball, some gunflint fragments, and ceramics. This area was outside of the
town during the Revolutionary War, so it is likely these artifacts were used by the soldiers or workers
building the fortifications. Another possibility is that citizens were camped here to avoid the Allies’
bombing.

Later trash deposits were found above the 1700s material and were likely left behind during the
completion of War of 1812 defenses and later construction of houses as the town encroached in the
1840s and 1850s. Several Catholic religious medals were lost over the years as well.
		</longDesc>
		<evImg>lafayette_ev1</evImg>
		<evDesc>Archaeologists digging, mapping, screening for artifacts, and talking to students from St. Vincent’s Academy in Lafayette Square.</evDesc>
    </site>
    <site>
        <name>Emmet Park</name>
        <lat>32.079447</lat>
        <lon>-81.085002</lon>
       	<img>emmetpark</img>
        <desc>The site of many forts due to strategic position over the Savannah River</desc>
        <longDesc>
            A series of forts sat on the high bluff overlooking the Savannah River at the northeastern corner of town,
because it was an excellent strategic location. As early as 1734, a 12 gun battery and two block houses
with four guns each was built. The fortification was greatly expanded by the British in 1779-1782 and
renamed Fort Prevost. After the American Revolution, the new United States resurrected the area as
Fort Wayne.

Archaeologists found a large, wooden-floored trench measuring 33 by 10 feet and artifacts such as a
brass percussion cap, a brass shotgun shell casing, clay pipes, nails, and late-1700s era pottery. Only part
of the trench was excavated, leaving some of this feature for future archaeologists. The feature might be
gun emplacement or other military construction during the American Revolution, the War of 1812, and
maybe even the Civil War. The trench was probably filled in when the city built Factors’ Walk (ca. 1854-
1869).

This area is also has a Native American site, represented by oyster shell and Deptford check stamped,
cordmarked, and plain pottery.
        </longDesc>
        <evImg>emmet_ev1</evImg>
        <evDesc>Small shovel test pits help us find archaeological sites.</evDesc>
    	
    	<evImg>emmet_ev2</evImg>
    	<evDesc>Close-up of artifacts in the screen from digging a shovel test pit. The oyster shell was left by Native Americans living here. </evDesc>
    </site>
</sites>