<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sites>
    <!-- #1 -->
    <site>
        <name>Battlefield Park</name>
        <lat>32.075611</lat>
        <lon>-81.099523</lon>
        <img>battlefieldpark</img>
        <desc>The site of the bloodiest battle of the American Revolution</desc>
        <longDesc>
Time period: American Revolution

Type of site: Military

History: 
	
	Battlefield Park is the site of the bloodiest battle of the American Revolution. You are standing
where the Colonial and French Allies attacked the Spring Hill Redoubt on October 9, 1779. Fourteen
redoubts, or small forts, connected by an abatis wall surrounded British-held Savannah during the
American Revolution. The Allied casualties numbered approximately 800, while the British only 50. The
Allies retreated in chaos, losing the battle but eventually winning the war.

After the Revolutionary War, houses and small business sprung up including a distillery and meat-
packing industries. In the 1830s, the area changed drastically again with the founding of the Central of
Georgia Railroad.

Archaeology: 

	Along Martin Luther King Jr. Blvd rises a reconstructed Spring Hill Redoubt, about ¾ its
original size. A few hundred feet down Louisville Road, a memorial marks the remains of the original
Spring Hill Redoubt discovered in 2005 by Coastal Heritage Society archaeologists. Look for plaques
around the park that give a detailed history of the battle and a column of stones commemorating the
Allies’ casualties.
		</longDesc>
        
        <!-- Image followed by description -->
        <evImg>battlefield_ev1</evImg>
        <evDesc>Brass barrel band from a Charleville pistol</evDesc>
    </site>
    <!--  #2 -->
    <site>
        <name>Central of Georgia Railroad</name>
        <lat>32.075666</lat>
        <lon>-81.09913</lon>
        <img>centralrailroad</img>
        <desc>The Central Railroad and Banking Company was founded in 1836 by William Washington Gordon. The Savannah History Museum is original Passenger Depot</desc>
    	<longDesc>
Time period: 1830s-1960s

Type of site: Industrial

History: 

	The Central Railroad and Banking Company was founded in 1836 by William Washington Gordon
(grandfather of Juliette Gordon Low, founder of the Girl Scouts). Central of Georgia Railway Savannah
Shops and Terminal Facilities, as this area came to be known, is a National Historic Landmark. The brick
building north of Battlefield Park is the original Passenger Depot and now houses a Visitor’s Center and
the Savannah History Museum.

Archaeology: 

	The repair shops are partially restored and feature working steam and diesel engines.
Many small archaeological projects have exposed older versions of the railroad over the year. For
example, archaeologists have found the footprint of the first, smaller roundhouse where the rolling
stock (correct name for a train car) was parked when undergoing minor repairs. The current roundhouse
is the building closest to Battlefield Park.

	The first transfer table, a mechanism for transporting rolling stock to the correct stall in the Carpentry
Shop and Paint Shop, was also discovered archaeologically. Part of this transfer table is preserved
outside of the Savannah Children’s Museum, which will be housed in the old Paint Shop.

Note: Today the repair shops are the Georgia State Railroad Museum run by Coastal Heritage Society
and do require an entry fee.
    	</longDesc>
    	<evImg>central_ev1</evImg>
    	<evDesc>The remains of the original Central of Georgia Railway transfer table (facing west). The Carpentry Shop is to the left outside of the frame.</evDesc>
    	<evImg>central_ev2</evImg>
    	<evDesc>The remains of the original Central of Georgia Railway transfer table (facing east).</evDesc>
    </site>
    <!-- #3 -->
    <site>
        <name>Railroad Ward</name>
        <lat>32.075193</lat>
        <lon>-81.100342</lon>
        <img>railroadward</img>
        <desc>The Railroad Ward is bounded by MLK Jr. Boulevard and West Harris, Purse, and Charlton streets. From the 1830s, the ward held small houses often owned or rented by people working at the adjacent Central of Georgia and their families.</desc>
		<longDesc>
Time period: 1830s-present

Type of site: Domestic

History: 

	Savannah is a carefully designed city, divided up into wards. Each ward consists of a central
square surrounded by 4 tythings (or 40 town lots) and four Trust Lots for the public good, which often
held public buildings. The earliest white, male settlers received a town lot (60x90 ft), a farm south of
town (44 acres) and a garden lot west of town (5 acres).

	The Railroad Ward is bounded by MLK Jr. Boulevard and West Harris, Purse, and Charlton streets. From
the 1830s, the ward held small houses often owned or rented by people working at the adjacent Central
of Georgia and their families.

Archaeology: 

	Prior to the construction to the Marriott Hotel, archaeologists were able to excavate part
of the hotel’s footprint. Many of the residents left behind items from their everyday lives such as toys,
plates, bowls, tea pots, bathroom tiles, buttons, and animal bones from their dinners.
		</longDesc>
		<evImg>railward_ev1</evImg>
		<evDesc>Brick-lined privy excavated at the Railroad Ward</evDesc>
		<evImg>railward_ev2</evImg>
		<evDesc>Bone, teeth, and oyster shell found at the site tell us what the residents were eating. Look for the butchery cut marks.</evDesc>
		<evImg>railward_ev3</evImg>
		<evDesc>Plate and bowl fragments found on the site.</evDesc>
		<evImg>railward_ev4</evImg>
		<evDesc>Personal items recovered include a heating comb for straightening hair, a partial buckle, straight pin, and hook from a hook-and-eye clothing closure.</evDesc>
		<evImg>railward_ev5</evImg>
		<evDesc>Many children’s toys were found on site. Clockwise from top left: marble, plate and cup from a doll-size tea set, child-size knife and spoon, and a porcelain doll foot.</evDesc>
    </site>
    <site>
        <name>Madison Square</name>
        <lat>32.073575</lat>
        <lon>-81.093877</lon>
        <img>madisonsquare</img>
        <desc>Location of a military ditch dug by British forces in 1779</desc>
		<longDesc>
	In 2008, archaeologists discovered a military ditch dug by British forces in 1779. Angling northwest-
southeast, this ditch was identified as the West-Central redoubt, which was the location of Allies’ feint
before real attack at Spring Hill.

	After the British left Savannah in the summer of 1782, the Americans filled in the ditches, burying
many artifacts as well. Brick from the barracks located just north was found in the ditch. Many of these
artifacts tell us about the lives of the soldiers.
		</longDesc>
        <evImg>maddison_ev1</evImg>
        <evDesc>Archaeologists excavating in Madison Square.</evDesc>
        
        <evImg>maddison_ev2</evImg>
        <evDesc>Military button found in Madison Square excavation, note the faint “V”.</evDesc>
    
    	<evImg>maddison_ev3</evImg>
    	<evDesc>Guncock from a British Brown Bess musket recovered from the Madison Square excavation.</evDesc>    	    
    </site>
    <site>
        <name>Lafayette Square</name>
        <lat>32.073084</lat>
        <lon>-81.091912</lon>
		<img>lafayettesquare</img>
		<desc>Historical maps suggest this is the location of the East-Central redoubt</desc>
		<longDesc>
	Historic map analysis suggested that the East-Central redoubt was located in Lafayette Square, so
archaeologists conducted a ground penetrating radar survey and dug several test pits (holes) in the
northwest quadrant of the square. Archaeologists found many artifacts from the 1730s to 1770s
including a .28 caliber lead ball, some gunflint fragments, and ceramics. This area was outside of the
town during the Revolutionary War, so it is likely these artifacts were used by the soldiers or workers
building the fortifications. Another possibility is that citizens were camped here to avoid the Allies’
bombing.

	Later, trash deposits were found above the 1700s material and were likely left behind during the
completion of War of 1812 defenses and later construction of houses as the town encroached in the
1840s and 1850s. Several Catholic religious medals were lost over the years as well.
		</longDesc>
		<evImg>lafayette_ev1</evImg>
		<evDesc>Archaeologists digging, mapping, screening for artifacts, and talking to students from St. Vincent’s Academy in Lafayette Square.</evDesc>
    </site>
    <site>
        <name>Emmet Park</name>
        <lat>32.079447</lat>
        <lon>-81.085002</lon>
       	<img>emmetpark</img>
        <desc>The site of many forts due to strategic position over the Savannah River</desc>
        <longDesc>
	A series of forts sat on the high bluff overlooking the Savannah River at the northeastern corner of town,
because it was an excellent strategic location. As early as 1734, a 12 gun battery and two block houses
with four guns each was built. The fortification was greatly expanded by the British in 1779-1782 and
renamed Fort Prevost. After the American Revolution, the new United States resurrected the area as
Fort Wayne.

	Archaeologists found a large, wooden-floored trench measuring 33 by 10 feet and artifacts such as a
brass percussion cap, a brass shotgun shell casing, clay pipes, nails, and late-1700s era pottery. Only part
of the trench was excavated, leaving some of this feature for future archaeologists. The feature might be
gun emplacement or other military construction during the American Revolution, the War of 1812, and
maybe even the Civil War. The trench was probably filled in when the city built Factors’ Walk (ca. 1854-
1869).

	This area is also has a Native American site, represented by oyster shell and Deptford check stamped,
cordmarked, and plain pottery.
        </longDesc>
        <evImg>emmet_ev1</evImg>
        <evDesc>Small shovel test pits help us find archaeological sites.</evDesc>
    	
    	<evImg>emmet_ev2</evImg>
    	<evDesc>Close-up of artifacts in the screen from digging a shovel test pit. The oyster shell was left by Native Americans living here. </evDesc>
    </site>
</sites>